Joshua Morse Papers, 1790-1849
Mortimer Rare Book Room
Joshua Morse Papers
1790-1849
Morse, Joshua
276
1 box (3 linear inches)
Mortimer Rare Book Room Smith College Northampton, MA
The Joshua Morse papers contain land deeds for property transactions in Newfane and Rockingham, Vermont between 1790 and 1941. There are bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounting records between 1817 and 1849. The guardianship papers (1831-1843) of Samuel W. Phillips and Mary Phillips are also in the papers.
Historical Note
There is little information on Joshua Morse, residing in Newfane, Vermont, who is largely responsible for these papers. The historic record is complicated by the fact that the name Joshua Morse of Newfane, Vermont, was used by other individuals who were likely related to the Joshua Morse of these papers.
Joshua Morse was born on November 20, 1777, in Princeton, Worcester, Massachusetts and died at Newfane, Vermont on September 12, 1859. He married Sarah (or Sally) Phillips at Easton, Massachusetts on August 12, 1798. To this union were born another Joshua Morse on September 3, 1801, David (June 18, 1807-1811), and Elijah (January 23, 1823-March 31, 1906).
Joshua Morse was appointed the legal guardian of Samuel W. Phillips and Mary W. Phillips in May 1831 after the death of their father Samuel Phillips. Samuel Phillips was born about 1791 and married Mary Phillips about 1822. Mary Phillips was born about 1801 in Marlboro, Windham County, Vermont. Samuel Wright Phillips was born July 6, 1821; the date of his death is not established. Mary Wright Phillips was born about 1823 in Marlboro, Windham County, Vermont. She married Abel S. Ward in June 1844 and died Feb 16, 1851. Samuel W. Phillips and Mary W. Phillips are likely Joshua Morse's nephew and niece.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Joshua Morse Papers are arranged in 4 series. SERIES I. LAND DEEDS includes deeds for transfer of land titles in Newfane and Rockingham, Vermont between 1790 and 1841. SERIES II. BILLS AND RECEIPTS has bills, receipts, promissory notes and accounting records for transactions between 1817 and 1849. Joshua Morse was appointed guardian for Samuel W. Phillips and Mary Phillips (likely his niece and nephew) and the papers in SERIES III (1831-1843) relate to that arrangement. SERIES IV. MISCELLANEOUS includes a holograph poem of a religious nature, an appeal (printed) of William H. Smith from 1859 and some newspaper clippings.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into four series:
I. LAND DEEDS
II. BILLS AND RECEIPTS
III. GUARDIANSHIP OF SAMUEL W. PHILLIPS AND MARY PHILLIPS BY JOSUHA MORSE
IV. MISCELLANEOUS
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Mortimer Rare Book Room.
The Joshua Morse papers were a gift of Mrs. Emma Bailey, Brattleboro, Vermont in 1964 and came to the Mortimer Rare Book Room through Nancy Dingman Watson (Smith College Class of 1964) of Putney, Vermont.
Mrs. Bailey indicated that Joshua Morse was an ancestor of the Bailey family of Vermont.
Morse, Joshua, 1777-1859; Phillips, Samuel Wright, 1821-; Phillips, Mary Wright, d. 1851; Land titles-Registration and transfer-Vermont-Windham County; Deeds; Financial records; Legal documents
- SERIES I. LAND DEEDS
  - Deed of Peter Penniman and Jacob White, transferring title of land in Newfane, Vermont to James Morse. 1790, 1795, The document is damaged and lacks the bottom portion of the page. The deed is endorse on the verso by the justice of peace 1790 Apr. 27 and by the town clerk of Newfane, Vermont, 1795 Jun. 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Deed 1803 Jan. 19 of Jacob Morse to Joshua Morse, transferring title of land in Windham County, Vermont. 1803, 1806, The deed is endorsed on the last page by the justice of peace, 1806 Nov. 23; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Deed 1822 Dec. 16 of John Morse to Joshua Morse, transferring title of land in Newfane, Vermont. 1822, 1823, The deed is endorsed on the verso by the town clerk in Newfane, Vermont, 1823 Jan. 2.; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Deed 1830 Jan. 21 of Henry F. Green to Samuel Guild, transferring title of land in Rockingham, county of Windham, Vermont.1830, The deed is endorsed on the verso by the town clerk in Rockingham, Vermont, 1830 Jan. 29.; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Deed 1831 Feb. 22of Henry F. Green to Samuel Guild, transferring title of land in Rockingham, county of Windham, Vermont.1831, The deed is endorsed on the verso by the town clerk in Rockingham, Vermont, 1831 Feb. 22.; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Deed of 1841 Jun. 23 Rasom King, executor of the estate of William King Cate to Josuha Morse, transferring title of land in Newfane, Vermont. 1841, The deed is endorsed on the verso by the town clerk of Newfane, Vermont, 1841 Nov. 9.; 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- SERIES II. BILLS AND RECEIPTS
  - Nineteen (19) slips of paper containing financial records including bills, receipts, promissory notes and miscellaneous accounting records, 1817-1849. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- SERIES III. GUARDIANSHIP OF SAMUEL W. PHILLIPS AND MARY PHILLIPS BY JOSHUA MORSE
  - Appointment of Joshua Morse as guardian for Samuel W. Phillips and Mary Phillips, heirs of Samuel Phillips, Malborough, Windham County, Vermont, 1831 May 4. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Request of Mary Phillips, 1842 Feb. 8. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Accounting record, 1842. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Complaint against Joshua Morse, Newfane, Vermont in regards to his neglect of his guardianship of Samuel W. Phillips and Mary Phillips in regards to the estate of Samuel Phillips, 1843 Apr. 28., Lemuel Whitney, register, Probate Court, Windham Country, Vermont. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- SERIES IV. MISCELLANEOUS
  - Manuscript of a religious poem and prose. The poem begins: When God shall call my soul to go. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Printed public appeal of Warren H. Smith, Rutland, Vt., 1858 Jul. 8, dealing with pensions and the Kansas question. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Two newspaper clippings on the abolitionist John Brown. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper clipping on David Wilmot (1814-1868). (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper clipping on Confederate General James Elwell Brown Stuart (1833-1864), known as "Jeb" Stuart. (Box 1, Folder 16)